<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iehovah Iireh merito audiens, præco evangelicus An angell from heaven, or, An ambassadour for Christ, descending from God, ascending unto God, lawfully dignified, compleately qualified : heard (vvith religious devotion) reporting his ambassage to the honourable societies of the Inner and Middle Temples, on Sunday the eleventh day of December, 1642 ... / by Edw. Tuke.</title>
            <author>Tuke, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63830</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3224</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10730</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13293208</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13293208</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98863</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63830)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98863)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 440:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iehovah Iireh merito audiens, præco evangelicus An angell from heaven, or, An ambassadour for Christ, descending from God, ascending unto God, lawfully dignified, compleately qualified : heard (vvith religious devotion) reporting his ambassage to the honourable societies of the Inner and Middle Temples, on Sunday the eleventh day of December, 1642 ... / by Edw. Tuke.</title>
                  <author>Tuke, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 12 [i.e. 21] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T.W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 1-5 have print show-through and are difficult to read.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts V, 20 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98863:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98863:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Iehovah Iireh <hi>Merito Audiens, praeco Evangelicus</hi> An Angell from Heaven, OR, An Ambaſſadour for CHRIST, Deſcending from God, Aſcending unto God, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully dignified, compleately qualified, HEARD (VVith Religious devotion) reporting his AMBASSAGE. To the honourable Societies of the Inner, and Middle TEMPLES: On Sonday the Eleventh day of <hi>December</hi> 1642. The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance whereof is commended to publicke view; By <hi>Edw. Tuke.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>LUKE 2. 13. </bibl> And ſuddenly there was with the Angell, a multitude of the heavenly Hoſtes praiſing God and ſaying,
<bibl>14.</bibl> Glory to God in the Higheſt, and on Earth peace, good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men.</q>
            <p>London printed for <hi>T. W.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98863:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98863:2"/>
            <head>To the <hi>Worſhipfull,</hi> well devoted &amp; his much <hi>Honoured</hi> friend M. <hi>Iohn Cave</hi> Councellor at Law and of the Inner-Temple</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Rabbins</hi> to maintaine <hi>Tradition,</hi> uſually diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh <hi>Gods</hi> Holy Law, into the Law written; <hi>Torah ſhe baccathubh</hi> and <hi>Torah ſhe begnah Peh;</hi> and their <hi>Talmud</hi> or Doctrinall, is no other then an elucidation or expoſition on Gods Law written, ſaith <hi>Elias Levila in Tiſbi:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to take <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Traditioe, as we uſe the word in the Church, <hi>pro quavis Iuſtitutione quae eccleſiâ traditur,</hi> it may as juſtly referre to Propheticall and Apoſtolicall Truths, and by conſequence, not to be Abrogated: 2 <hi>Theſ 2. 15, 1 Cor.</hi> 2. 15. 3, 4 As to thoſe things whoſe circumſtances make them mutable and whoſe obſervations is <hi>therefore</hi> free, and not of abſolute neceſſity as <hi>Act. 15. 28 29. 1 Cor.</hi> 11. 2.</p>
            <p>Of this Sermon, you had firſt an <hi>unwritten Tradition</hi> or (as the Iews ſay) the Law ſpoken, The errors which may be found in it, are with tolerable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty better to be anſwered, in that it was given me (as they ſay their Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) in the <hi>Night,</hi> for I thinke, there is no man that ſhall attempt and act matters of high and uſefull conſequence from houres <hi>ſtollen</hi> from his <hi>pillow,</hi> but may now and then be taken napping<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuch as it was, being given me to deliver, it was more then Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable I ſhould deliver to them, for whom it was Given; yea to do that, was <hi>Cauſa ſine quâ non;</hi> beſides Gods providence and ſpirituall permiſſion; Your Patience an particular Admiſſion, There was law to command me, the law of neceſſity, and neceſſity of preaching, againſt which I know no law, and I muſt aknowledge, I had a conſcionable Motion to it at that time.</p>
            <p>It appertaines to all, lawfully called and duly authorized, to preach Gods word, And though I am yet (by Gods will) <hi>Fortunes</hi> Dwarf, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (Religiouſly be it ſpoken) and ſo, not commended to any proper Paſtorall cure; Yet in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> firſt chapter to the Romanes verſe 14. I can read my Duty; To which the Syrian gives a word of ſuch Important obligement; as may ſupply others (aſwell as thoſe of neceſſary invitation) with a paraphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Commentary upon this ſubject: <hi>mehhaicbh euoleakr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z,</hi> I am indebted to the pulpit, or in Duty to the office of a Preacher.</p>
            <p>From this Ground I <hi>ſpake,</hi> and <hi>ſpake</hi> my Conſcience God bearing me
<pb facs="tcp:98863:3"/> witnes; and from Gods Bearing me witnes, I <hi>writ;</hi> and Here you have the <hi>Law written.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt note unto <hi>you</hi> Sir, that I do not with reall Freedome expoſe my ſelf to the preſſe, much leſſe, to the Torturing Rack of the worlds harſh Cenſure; learning it ſelf <hi>stands in White ſheets</hi> and I think no <hi>publick penance</hi> is volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary; Mine is not ſuch, yet if it ſuffer ſuch, and look not too <hi>pale,</hi> the matter is leſſe; <hi>White</hi> is a Symboll of Innocency and Purity, and theſe is ſome comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able mitigation, to be perſwaded; <hi>It doth penance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sinfull Cenſurers of the Times, are as Locuſts in <hi>Aegypt;</hi> I ſpeak not <hi>double</hi> when I ſay <hi>Arbeh</hi> is nor ſtrained from <hi>Rabah, Multitudes</hi> from <hi>Numbers;</hi> Some for <hi>Paul,</hi> ſome for <hi>Apollos,</hi> ſome for <hi>Lephas;</hi> From the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of theſe <hi>Numbers,</hi> are drawn many <hi>Heads,</hi> which ſome call <hi>Diviſions:</hi> Theſe like wormes, live upon the Government, and eat out the very <hi>Hart</hi> of the Tree, or as Flies in ſummer, putrify the ſweeteſt ſuſtenance.</p>
            <p>Sir, Theſe ſend me to you; for the Declenſion of an age from primitive vertue, could not ſuffer me to come forth without Protection; <hi>an hundred to one, Theſe are many:</hi> you may pleaſe in this matter to be <hi>all one</hi> to me: That one is that I wiſh for my <hi>ſingular</hi> eſteem of you, makes me <hi>account theſe Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralists nullius numen,</hi> nothing.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort; Your Love, next unto Gods <hi>Hand,</hi> lead me to the <hi>Temple,</hi> at that Time, and your Approbatory Teſtimony, compells me to prize my poor <hi>Fortunes</hi> dexterity, that hath fitted a Dedication correſpondent to my deſires Direction, at this Time.</p>
            <p>The Almighty God of heaven and earth, whoſe property in Divine Nature is to be mercifull above offences, quicken you by his Spirit, to an heavenly <hi>Emulacia</hi> to ſtudy the Principles and Deſires of his Truth, and (as farr as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes you) the Churches ſafety; incloſe you in the volume of his Book; and Gather you into the Boſome of his Son, in whom is only True Bliſſe, and of whom.</p>
            <p>By Faith and Holines (in this life) you ſhall be aſſured at the Reſurrection of the Juſt; when God by his Spirit or <hi>ſoft and ſtill voice,</hi> in a leſſe minute then any man dies here, ſhall unite the Spirits and Bodyes of all: <hi>When</hi> and <hi>Where God is All in All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though his <hi>Church</hi> on Earth (as at this time never ſo <hi>militant</hi>) be ſad <hi>round</hi> about, and his Children under Clouds and pillars of fire; yet <hi>Surſum Corda</hi> lift up your hart, and eyes unto the Hils, thoſe mountaines of Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance above; Take every day two or three Turnes up and down <hi>Iacobs ladder,</hi> by humble Meditations and Faithfull Ejaculations, Truſting unto your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer with Godly perſeverance; And let the Troubles, be what can be, for
<pb facs="tcp:98863:3"/> Condition and Duration<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo long as there is <hi>Elijah</hi> an holy and devout ſoule; God will be in the <hi>Cave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is my ſecurity <hi>in this Buſines</hi> to have thought upon your Candour; when you have kindly accepted this, you free me not of all; for in <hi>Gratitude</hi> I owe you ſervice, and in <hi>Duty</hi> prayer,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Whileſt I am a <hi>lawfull Ambaſſadour for Chriſt,</hi> EDVARD TVKE.</signed>
               <dateline>From my Study <date>December 19. 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:98863:4"/>
            <p>HOnoratiſſimis, ſagaciter per ſapientibus, literis manſuetioribus Diſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſime locupletibus, ſacroſanctâ Doctrinarum veritate (Anglicanae Eccleſia fideliter extru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tâ) Accuratiſſimè Fundatis</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roberto Berkley,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roberto Foſter,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Franciſco Crawley,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Iuriſprudentibus, militibus, &amp; Iudicibus, omni obſervantiâ colendis, vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randis.</p>
            <p>Et claritate virtutis excellenti, ingenuè Dapſili, Arte &amp; legibus comptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè, integerrimè<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> valenti, Regales cauſas, ſcientiſsime Oranti</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Radolpho Whitfield, militi,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Necnon, Generoſi ſanguinis, utriuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Templi, Iuris Candidatis, culti oris facun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diâ, &amp; venuſtiſsimo Ciceronis lepôre Relucentibus &amp; Fragrantibus; ſuavilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentiâ Feſtiviſsimâ, uberrimâ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſententiarum ſupellectile (aurei inſtar Flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis) exuberantibus; Humanitatis laude urbanioris, antecellentibus; officiorum ſtudioſioribus; Iuvenibus.</p>
            <p>Hunc ſuum, Meritò Audientem Praeconem Evangelicum,</p>
            <p>In Concione (oratione impolitâ apud vos, praelectâ, Decembris undecimo Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nico, habitâ,) Munuſculum Levidenſae, ad perpetuum (in caleſtibus) veſtrum Monumentum &amp; em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lumentum</p>
            <p>Theologicâ laureâ <hi>minimè</hi> Doctoratus, ſuppliciter, <hi>verecundè,</hi> nec minùs <hi>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicundè ſummo candore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Offert, Addicat, Conſecrat<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>, Decemb. 19. 1642.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>EDVARDVS TVKE Presbyter Humillimus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98863:4"/>
            <head>CHRISTS Lawfull <hi>AMBASSADOVR.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THeſe meditations Infant-like unable to walke or talke by themſelves as <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> in <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſilently and humbly intreate your Attentions, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not paſſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing of <hi>Rabbin Joſibar, Iehudah</hi> in <hi>Pirkabboth,</hi> he that learnes of young men like a man that eates un-ripe grapes, or drinks Wine out of the Wine-preſſe. But hee that learnes of the Ancient is like him that eates ripe grapes and drinks wine that is old: And it is <hi>Plinies</hi> direction; for more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous wine of the old Vine Tree (Antiquity was famous and had reſpect in thoſe dayes,) <hi>Ex vetustioribus vitibus vinum melius, novellis Copioſius.</hi> And ſhould I by Synechdochen underſtand Baptiſme, for the ſum of S. <hi>Iohn Baptiſts</hi> Doctrine, I hope I could not offend in humility to profeſſe with <hi>Apollos, Act.</hi> 18. 25. That I underſtand only <hi>Iohns</hi> Baptiſme. And therefore I ſubmiſſively ſalute you in his Apology unto Chriſt whom he indeavoured to put of comming to his Baptiſme with his <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I have need to be baptized of thee, and commest thou to me?</hi> but patiently ſuffer it to be ſo now, Me to preach and you to heare the word of the Lord, delivered unto you, from the,</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 COR. 5. 20.</bibl>Now therefore we are Ambaſſadours for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you by us, we pray in Chriſts ſtead, be ye reconciled to God.</q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Text in its body repreſents a Church and State in an ordinate unity under one head, or <hi>Domuni quandam conventionis,</hi> a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Houſe of Parliament, the debatements though various, yet intend the Churches happineſſe and determine in peace. The King and Lord Spirituall of the upper Houſe in Heaven inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates the Treaty for the ſetled bliſſe of the Soule, is content though ſtabdd and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98863:5"/> pierced through with the ſharp ſpeare of daily tranſgreſſions, and inſufferable injuries to paſſe his pardon without mans <hi>peccavi</hi> or demand, and not upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our oblivion and want of gratitude endeavours by all continued Clemency, to ſeeke us yea ſeeke to finds us who firſt loſt him by ſending this unparralleld Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage of peace. Now therefore we are Embaſſadours for Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Poets faine the Chariot of the ſunne in reſpect of its foure diverſities to be drawne by foure horſes: at his riſing it is redd, at the third houre bright, at noone hot, at Evening cold; the fiction I ſtand not to diſpute, only in this Text I can perceive foure wheeles as of a Chariot; running much like thoſe foure laſt Articles of faith, upon which wiſe men by rumination walke, and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſt, whileſt fooles runne over and over throwe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Read here the Communion of Saints, which may be gathered hence, <hi>we are Ambaſſadours</hi> ſent to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, See the forgiveneſſe of Sins, if ye repent, while God beſeecheth, and we <hi>pray in Christs ſtead<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Expect the bodies reſurrection properly, and the ſoules Metaphori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally and accidentally from the grave of death, ſinne, and hell, which is perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſured to the utmoſt of this lifes capacity, if ye be reconciled; therefore bee reconciled.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Taſte that <hi>all</hi> good, and <hi>good of all,</hi> life everlaſting <hi>God,</hi> the reſt of the reſt, therefore be <hi>yee reconciled unto God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> But I have here 4 other wheeles very uſefull and not unfitly made faſt to this Charriot.</p>
            <p>1. Is <hi>Magnificens Chriſti in preſbyterio Majeſtus,</hi> Gods power and Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie in his Miniſtery, <hi>We are Ambaſſadours for Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>Affectio providens,</hi> Gods provident love to his people, <hi>as though God did beſeech you by us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. Here is <hi>Religioſe unita ſocietas,</hi> an unanimous and religious ſociety, Chriſt by his Ambaſſadours, the Ambaſſadours in Chriſt, requeſt your Chriſtian conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, unto Chriſt, <hi>We pray in Christs ſtead<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be reconciled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. Here is <hi>indefatigabilis &amp; immutabilit ſatie as,</hi> an unwearied and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable ſaciety of Gods mercy and your peace, <hi>if ye be reconciled, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; Now therefore wee are Ambaſſadours for Christ, as though God did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you by us, we pray you in Chriſts ſtead to be reconciled unto God.</hi> The firſt word <hi>now,</hi> ſtands as <hi>Abraham</hi> in his Tent dore, attending the comming of <hi>Angels</hi> from God, ſuch as theſe <hi>textuary Embaſſadours,</hi> and ſerves <hi>now</hi> to inſtruct us of an orderly ſucceſſion of Legats from God unto a ſtrange people, and it opens the doore unto Chriſt too, and ſignifies his ſpeciall appointment of Shepheards over his flock, as <hi>Biſhops, Paſtors, and Apostles,</hi> to guide, feed, and inſtruct them, <hi>now therefore we are Embaſſadours,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this word now, by an holy and Apoſtolicall derivation is preſent with us to confirm our office and authority, and to injoyn you obedience and ſubmiſſion
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98863:5"/> to the watch man and his word for your <hi>ſoules,</hi> now therfore <hi>we are Ambaſſadors for Christ, as though God did beſeech you by us, we pray in Christs ſtead, be yee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled unto God</hi> From this Illative <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>therefore,</hi> I might argue a conſequent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the Ambaſſadours comming, and your entertainement of his perſon and Meſſage, as alſo, I might hence yeeld a reaſon invincible, of your ſpirituall life, by <hi>dying</hi> to the night of ſin, and riſing to the day of righteouſnes, propounded unto you, as a matter of great juſtice, from the death and Reſurrection of our Saviour <hi>Ieſus Christ, ver.</hi> 13. as alſo, the meanes of accompliſhing that death and this Reſurrection, which this therefore ſeemes to imply, as the complement of your ſalvation, when in religious obedience, hereto you approve the <hi>dignity</hi> of the Miniſter over you to that effect, or to effect that, <hi>&amp; excellentiam Ministerij,</hi> as <hi>Beza</hi> notes it, the excellency of the Miniſterie, and thence termed the word of reconciliation, <hi>ver.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>But having more than two words to ſpeak, I ſpeak of theſe two little more, though laid in my way like ſtones, not of offence, but defence, and as the Baſis of a chiefe corner ſtone, fetcht hither from the bottome of the earth, or <hi>Moſes</hi> rock, which being poliſhed, fitted and ſquared by ſufficient explication, might prove ſolid <hi>grounds,</hi> for erecting us lively ſtones in Gods building, by faithfull applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Now therefore we are Ambaſſadours. In the firſt five words, are five ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall parts of ſpeech, which Grammatically ſtood upon, would help me to avoyd the tongues confuſion, by which the whole worke ſuffers, and <hi>goes not</hi> forward, but omitting that, as alſo the ſubject, copulate, and redicate, which logically, this firſt affirmative propoſition affords, I will apply my ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſomewhat, to the <hi>concurrence</hi> of thoſe wheeles, on which the Text laſt ranne, and not liking many <hi>diviſions</hi> in the Temple, pleaſe to obſerve in the <hi>moving</hi> of the firſt wheele, <hi>Deputationem noſtram,</hi> our Deputation, we are Ambaſſadours, 2. <hi>Reputationem noſtram,</hi> our reputation <hi>for Christ;</hi> In the turning of the ſecond wheele, note 2. Firſt, <hi>Commiſſionem,</hi> our <hi>commiſſion; Velut Deo vos precante per nos,</hi> as though God did beſeech you by us. Secondly, <hi>Conditionem,</hi> the Condition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Oramus nomine Chriſti,</hi> wee pray in Chriſts ſtead, in the third or three <hi>quarter wheele,</hi> take notice of the ſubjects <hi>Vos</hi> yee, be yee. 2. The ſubject, reconciliation, <hi>Vos reconciliamini,</hi> be <hi>ye reconciled:</hi> in the laſt wheele, as it <hi>turnes round,</hi> ſee the object, God, whom I have read ſignified, by a wheele which turnes ever and never ceaſeth turning, <hi>Vos reconcilumini Deo,</hi> be ye reconciled unto God.</p>
            <p>Thus reverently ſaving to my Text, the Acclamation of <hi>Eliſha</hi> unto <hi>Elijah<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> in his rapture, to a bleſſed tranſlation, <hi>my Father, my Father, the Charriot of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, and the horſe-men of Iſrael,</hi> I ſhall now upon theſe particulars, or ſome of them, ſometime ſit, and ſometime ſtand, and in this devided Order. Firſt, of the firſt.</p>
            <p>Wee are Embaſſadours, various and as valuable are theſe high Titles of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour various which the great God of HEAVEN and Earth, hath collated
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98863:6"/> upon the Heralds of his Law and Goſpel which are Bridles to command and curbe the ſcorne of the contemptible world, nor can any eye be ſo Dimme and fleſhly covered though overſpread with a <hi>Scirrhoſis</hi> but may diſcerne thoſe titular reſpects to be tutelar protects of ſuch his Ambaſſadours and Meſſengers as the Apple of his owne eye: They are ſilver keyes which lead the Coveteous Chriſtian to the golden treaſure hidden in the field: be it only <hi>Titulus iſis.</hi> And it <hi>Quaſi Titan</hi> illuminating the minds of the men or leſſe Ignorant, as the ſunne doth the world, but they are many, and like <hi>Pilates</hi> ſuperſcription in Hebrew, Greek, &amp; Latin, to point the Iew, Gentile and Chriſtian to Chriſt and his Croſſe, for which we are Ambaſſadours.</p>
            <p>Ambaſſadours, honourable men, and of Gods Privy Councell, fellow Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners with God, yea Angels too: and this teſtimony, we receave in either Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. Expoſitours meane the judging high Prieſt, when <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> the 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. tis ſaid, ſay not before the Angell; and the Jews propound that Angell, which came up from <hi>Gilgal</hi> to be <hi>Phineas</hi> the high Prieſt, <hi>Iudg. 2. &amp;</hi> 1. And ſo <hi>Beza</hi> renders thoſe Angells before whom a woman muſt be covered in the Church, to be the inſtructing Miniſters. The Angells of the ſeaven Churches, we ſay Biſhops, (whereas others that cannot ſpeake out, with <hi>Shibboleth,</hi>) call them ſuperintendents. And becauſe we preach the Unity of one full Church Celeſtiall and Terreſtriall under <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> we participate by the counterchange of names, of the nature of Angells. An Angell in Heaven is a Celeſtiall Prieſt and an Ambaſſadour in Earth is well ſtiled a Terreſtriall Angell. We are thoſe Angells upon the ladder of <hi>Iacob, Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> aſcending by prayer for the people, by, and to his Divinity, and deſcending by Doctrine upon the people, by his Humanity, though Coucht under the flatt ſtile of an Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour in the text. Nor is this relation of ſo late newes as to cauſe your eares to itch, but rather tingle, <hi>in dicbus illis,</hi> even in the old time before us this Doctrine was preached, the uſe diſcovered, the abuſe corrected; the old world were <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium tenus</hi> up to the eares in water, and periſhed as by an heavenly. Dropſy, for not obeying &amp; eſteeming <hi>Noah</hi> an Ambaſſadour fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God unto them: the luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Sodomites</hi> were (for wickednes almoſt matchleſſe) matched, being conſumed by flames, and generally overthrown by one burning fever, for that they hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened not unto righteous <hi>Lot</hi> their Ambaſſadour. Since ever there were a people God hath continued away of practiſe with that people either immediatly or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly, extraordinarily or ordinarily, ſometime by inſpiration, ſometime by dreames, ſometime by propheſy, ſometime by viſions, and ſometime by revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, all which in their Order &amp; end conſidered, were as ſo many Embaſſadours from God the great King, and as ſo many teſtimonies of his mercy and love to the people, even from <hi>Moſes</hi> the great Prophet, unto <hi>Malachi</hi> the leſſer, the line hath runne direct, to point to the greateſt of all <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> whom Saint
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98863:6"/> 
               <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> exactly aymed at with his <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Behold the lambe of God which taketh away the ſinnes of the world. Not a word without an Article to leade us to the perſon and Actions of Chriſt, for whom being come and aſcended we are Ambaſſadours.</p>
            <p>In this place, I may without digreſſion obſerve Gods holy and wiſe Oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall Method: untill the Law was publiſhed, God revealed himſelf and his will by Apparitions and Inſpirations of Prophets; but Miracles and viſions apparant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decreaſed as there was an augmentation of his holy Scripture; ſo <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> at the captivity ended, and nothing was aſſigned to the Prieſts dutie, but to teach the Law when the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> finiſhed the Prophets; and <hi>Eſaiah</hi> the 8. 20. the people are informed to what they muſt look and ſtand, even to the Law and to the Teſtimony, and are evidently admoniſhed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> from which they might conclude; no more expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Angells, Prophets, dreames or viſions, untill the comming of that great Prophet indeed <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> ſo lately pointed at by his forrunner <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From this courſe we may gather the Complement of the Law, the ceaſing of further viſions, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oaching of dreames, of faineing of Propheſyes, of dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of new Revelations, and Enthuſiaſticall inſpirations, and here is the Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Goſpell by Gods lawfull Ambaſſadours, at whoſe mouth we are directed to know Chriſts will; whoſe lipps in the Temple we are bound to preferre before the private Adoration of a God of our own ſetting up, though we ſhould ſee him moove by his itching in our garrets &amp; chambers. We Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours have Authority to preach remiſſion of ſins to all faithfull penitents, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Reſurrection to Eternall life, to faithfull ſoules by <hi>Ieſus Christ,</hi> who having ſealed up all viſion and propheſy, revealed the whole will of his father di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected us unto Gods wiſdome, commands us to lay aſide all Popiſh traditions. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſticall inſpirations, humane unneceſſary inventions, and to reſt upon him in his written holy word; who is the beginning and the ending Alpha and Omega, the firſt and the laſt, And for this we are Ambaſſadours.</p>
            <p>Hence the people are taught that it muſt needs be an high arrogancy to add new Doctrines, becauſe the whole will of God the Father is in theſe laſt times fully declared and manifeſtly publiſhed by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> his only ſonne, and our only Saviour in his Word. And ſince Chriſt hath compleatly finiſhed the whole Law of God and mans everlaſting Redemption, and that this Doctrine, theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Embaſſadors are commanded with ſubſtantiall knowledg to preach to the people, the people are hence directed with all humble holineſſe immediatly to take drift and living directions from us as the textuaries, and Apoſtolicall Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, that ſo Gods written word may have evident and ſound Explication, all Schiſmes and hereſies utter exerpation, pure Devotion high augmentation ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98863:7"/> diſcipline in all comelineſſe and decency, practicall commendation, the people to whom the Embaſſadour comes, may receave ſincere edification, the Embaſſadour, religious eſtimation; Gods Ambaſſage deſerved exaltation, and God himſelf, an uniforme Glorification; and for this we are Ambaſſadours.</p>
            <p>Here is <hi>Officium &amp; Beneficium,</hi> Ambaſſadour 'tis <hi>nomen oneris</hi> aſwell as <hi>honoris,</hi> a name of Office aſwell as benefice, of ſedulity aſwell as utility, of ſervice aſwell as ceremony. We exerciſe an Elderſhip and diſcharge the work, as truely, as <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatione fungimur</hi> we are charged with the Embaſſage: by the authority of Chriſt, we are inveſted and inducted into one; and by the ſame vertue, <hi>in nomine Chriſti</hi> in the name of Chriſt, we effect the other: <hi>Dignitas honoris,</hi> the worthineſſe of this honour, falls out according to the power of this Gift; and the Gift had not been ſufficient, except God had indued it with power.</p>
            <p>Whence our Deputation firſt iſſued, and what it may underſtand; Saint <hi>Paul</hi> (as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menting elſe where upon this text) unfolds by the word of Eternall truth: He that deſcended is the ſame alſo who aſcended up farre above all heavens, that he might fullfill all things: 1. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 10. and <hi>v.</hi> 11. He gave ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors, and teachers for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtery, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But this deputation is no leſſe then a work of the ſacred <hi>Trinity,</hi> for the bleſſed Trinity, which by one conſultation in word created man, do now in the word, by one work, recreate him: in this laſt quotation you read <hi>Donum Filij,</hi> the gift of the Sonne, and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 6. you may read <hi>Donum Patris,</hi> the gift of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I have planted, <hi>Apollo</hi> watered, but God gave the increaſe; and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 28. And God hath ſet ſome in the Church, firſt Apoſtles, ſecondarily Prophets, thirdly teachers; after that Miracles then Gifts of Healings, Helps, Government, diverſities of tongues.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 28. ſee <hi>Donum Spiritus ſancti,</hi> the Gift of the holy Ghoſt: Take heed therefore unto your ſelves and to all the flock over the which the holy Ghoſt hath made you overſeers to feed the Church of God.</p>
            <p>Learned <hi>Calvin</hi> particularly interpreting Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> order of Apoſtles, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Evangeliſts, ſhepheards, and teachers; doth ſummarily concorporate them into the office and honour of an Apoſtolicall Paſtour, ſuch as this Embaſſadour himſelf was.</p>
            <p>By ſhepheards and teachers ſome underſtand thoſe, whoſe charge extended to the care of a particular Nation, and ſuch fell ſomewhat ſhort of that accompt, which they receaved, who ſpared no paines to preach every where.</p>
            <p>By Evangeliſts, ſome intimate thoſe who walked not abroad and yet preached, as <hi>Priſcilla Act.</hi> 18. 26. or thoſe who wrot the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>By Prophets, ſome meane certaine which were not Apoſtles, and yet were Prophets, as <hi>Agabus Act.</hi> 11. 28.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98863:7"/>
            <p>By Apoſtles, there are who underſtand ſuch as had all things, for an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle is a veſſell of the body more principall and lively, receaving all things from Chriſt himſelf; ſo ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſostome</hi> in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>And the before cited judicious <hi>Calvin,</hi> puts betwixt the orders ſome diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, but that, in very modeſt diſcretion.</p>
            <p>By teachers, he will ſignifie ſuch, as applied their whole diligence to the ſound interpretations of Divine writ, and whoſe care it was to preſerve the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Doctrine amongſt the faithfull, and tis his obſervation, that ſuch teachers intermedled not with any Diſcipline or Miniſtrations of Sacraments to the people.</p>
            <p>By Evangeliſts, he meanes an order in Dignity ſomewhat inferiour to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, yet not without ſome relations to them in office, ſuch as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> and perhapps thoſe 70. Diſciples appointed by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>By Prophets, he intends not all interpreters of the Divine will, but ſuch as by ſingular Revelation excelled others; of which kind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we have now none <hi>Extant,</hi> for ſo he argues, <hi>quales nunc vel nulli extant, vel minus ſunt conſpicui.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the power Apoſtolicall, he confines not to any other bounds then the whole Vniverſe, alluding to their Commiſſion granted from the Lord Governer and Commander of the whole world, Saint <hi>Mark 15 16. Go ye into all the world and preach the Goſpell to every Creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Paſtorall and Apoſtolicall charge, not admitting the leaſt difference betwixt them in ſubſtance or ſervice; He concludes, comprehends all theſe, for thus he reſolves. <hi>Paſtorale autem mumus haec omnia in ſe continet,</hi> and now by conſequence it is manifeſt: but what relation is or could be, in honour and office betwixt our teachers and the old Prophets; the ſame, more fully authorized and exemplified, have our Paſtours with the Apoſtles, and ſo, in the duties of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, praying, praiſing, baptizing, breaking of bread, adminiſtring of the Cup, and in all other holy actions grounded on Gods word; as apperteining to the Miniſtery, our ſucceſſion is Apoſtolicall; for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ingroſſeth not the office to himſelf, but verifieth an equality of execution to all ſuch ſucceeding Miniſters and Ambaſsadours. Let a man ſo eſteeme of us, as of the Miniſters of Chriſt and ſtewards of the Myſteries of God 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 1. that hence, we be eſteemed as <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours for Chriſt,</hi> ſent by Chriſt, and that the people to whom we are ſent, may as from our hand, receave the rich treaſure of Salvation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> gathered for them, and diſtributed unto them from the holy Scriptures and Myſteries of God; And in this ſenſe is my theſis in the text, <hi>we are Embaſſadours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is honour indelible, dignity indamnable, reward interminable, <hi>dignatio magna,</hi> here, if I could build Tabernacles, the glory of the Lord would ſuddain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fill them. <hi>We are Embaſſadours,</hi> here is or ſhould be our Unity, and we <hi>are all Embaſſadours,</hi> here is or ſhould be our holy Community; <hi>Legatione fungimur, we
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98863:8"/> are all Embaſſadours,</hi> but all are not we; he miſtaks the place, <hi>qui tibi hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c aſſumit honorem,</hi> who takes this honourable Office upon him, not being called of God as was <hi>Aaron:</hi> there are which runne, whom God hath not commanded to go, but interpreting Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> marke, ſett before them, to be a pulpit, preſſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in their ſenceleſſe performances, without authenticall Ordinations. <hi>O monstrum horrendum, Informe ingens cui lumen ademptum,</hi> O head and body without eyes, unparalleld wonder, here let Admiration ſeale up every lipp, that any people ſhould conceave that way, beſt profitable to mend their aberra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſteppings awry, by hearing and ſeeing a <hi>Cobler,</hi> who perhaps would delight more to be <hi>Solus cum ſola</hi> wax a Preacher, nay tis <hi>cauſa capitis</hi> and head Buſines, which moves my more then ordinary invectives: againſt ſuch propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and profaners, when a dreſſer of Hatts will ſeeme a redreſſer of hearts; what can ſuch polluted hands work ſave <hi>gum</hi> into mens Heads and <hi>gall</hi> into there minds, they may preſume to make Sermons as good as ever was felt, though never ſo true as to be underſtood, ſuch take not a book in hand without ſome coulour, and though there utterance exceed there entrance, their going out; there learning nay though there ſhutle tongues we aver like, <hi>Iigg</hi> into the tumult of diſcourſe, and ſtray into the timeleſſe waſt of words, againſt their own ſcience, or capacity; yet though many their are, bleſſed be God (which cry ſuch out) too too many there are, which cry up ſuch, for the only zealous tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and commend in them Gods power, with a <hi>digitus Dei,</hi> becauſe ſuch a Mechanicall Enthuſiaſt hath it <hi>ad unguem</hi> as he hath at his fingers end.</p>
            <p>What otherwiſe can be expected for event then making of Schiſmes and rents in Gods Church, when a the theeviſh tailour, who but now hath robbed his neighbour of his goods in his Stall, ſhall leap up into <hi>Moſes</hi> Chaire, and ſtraite way robb God of his honour in the pulpit, which of you, ever heard of any King that tooke a Cobler, hatter tailour, or ſuch like; and ſent him an Embaſſadour: and will the King of Kings (judge you) allow of ſuch; theſe like <hi>Apes,</hi> ſhew their uglineſſe by climbing up, theſe like horſleeches ſuck up that blood unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, which nature and Art as Parents. Have beſtowed upon lawfull Children, theſe like ſnap-dragons, live upon the Almsbaskett of the Countrey, their title to the Office and honour of the true Ambaſſadour, ſutes well with the harlotts claime, who when ſhe had overlaid here own Child, with a bold and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted for-head, pretended an intereſt in anothers; perſwade your ſelves, that even by ſuch inſtrument, the Divell may delude to deſtruction; whom ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte to have a Cloven foot, but think not of his Cloven tongue, yea my friend, to heare ſuch <hi>tautologicall fellowes,</hi> is unprofitable for you, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi> elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and ſince you heare his limitation, heare a little more from this text, even your Imitation, for <hi>we are Embaſſadours for Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98863:8"/>
            <p>I need not here further diſpute our primitive Inſtallment into this Sacred function, being Confident that no truely affected Sonne to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> can be ſeduced by ſuch ſenceleſſe inſolency, to deny or doubt, ſo poſſitive a truth as is here uttered, <hi>we are Embaſſadours for Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But not being ſuch, or in caſe there be ſuch, this text will better informe both; in which, there are <hi>credenda &amp; agenda</hi> matters of faith, that we are Embaſſadours, and ſuch Embaſſadours, and this reſpects our ſelves, and you to beleive; and matters of fact; and this concerns us, firſt to approve our ſelves Embaſſadours, and ſuch Embaſſadours, and then, it calls upon you to incline to our Embaſſage.</p>
            <p>The words reſpectively conſidered, may be compared, to an Image of <hi>Iuno</hi> in <hi>Lucian de Dea Syria;</hi> which looks this way, and that way, and every way; for they have an eye to us, and an eye to you, to us, as <hi>Activi Doctores,</hi> to you, as <hi>paſſivi diſcipuli,</hi> to us, as Embaſſadours faithfully to reporte our Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage, to you, as perſons, to whom we are ſent, fruitfully to receave our errand, they view us Embaſſadours, as we are dignified with honour, and they look upon us, as we performe our Office.</p>
            <p>But committing the honour, and worth of an Embaſſadour, to the wiſe eſtimation of thoſe perſons, whom juſtly it may reſpect; I ſhould paſſe to his work, ſave, that the Courſe might ſeeme prepoſterous, except I touch a little, upon ſome qualifications, proper to an Embaſſadour, and ſuch an Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, in this tranſition.</p>
            <p>The Perſians named there King and Prieſts <hi>Magos,</hi> neither do the Dignity of this Embaſſadour, nor the Excellency of his Office, lie obſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure under this Appellation; ſince the <hi>Hebrew</hi> gives it, a <hi>Meditando &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendo,</hi> from his Meditation and Inſtruction, for which two, he ſhould be ably quallified.</p>
            <p>The five Intellectuall vertues, <hi>Intellectus, Sapientia, Scientia, Ars,</hi> and <hi>Prudentia,</hi> Intelligence, Sapience, Science, Art, and Prudence, which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, Ethic.</hi> 6. terms, <hi>Arma Spiritualia,</hi> Spirituall Armour, or weapons; muſt never be wanting to this Embaſſadour, nor muſt he need that <hi>lac Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophia,</hi> milke of Philoſophy, Grammar, Logick, and Rethorique, by which ſoft nutriment, the Ancient aſwell as youth, ſucking, may be nouriſhed, and by theſe his tender Documents growing up, may in time, more freely and with leſſe Crudities digeſt his ſtronger Oratory.</p>
            <p>But for his more ſolid and prompt expreſſions, of thoſe Metaphyſicall and Theologicall Eſſayes, it will not diſhonour him, yea much inable him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to incline a regular obſervation, of Prudence, Juſtice, Fortitude, and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98863:9"/> 4. Cardinall vertues, ſo called, as in reſpect of the matters, Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, about which they treate, ſo, of that certaine and definite Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality, which they not improperly aſſume to themſelves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as <hi>Boelius de Conſol.</hi> 1. hath it.</p>
            <p>The Greek, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, originally iſſues from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> hence <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is aſmuch is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to ſerve and labour in tho duſt, ſo radically, (and in <hi>genere</hi>) underſtood, we are ſervants, toylers, and tillers of the Ground.</p>
            <p>And ſo Patheticall a power hath each word in his ſence, as if the earthly hearted hearer, ſhould neceſſarily and effectually be moiſtened, by the plento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dropps of the head ſweating preacher.</p>
            <p>Here the ſunne bakt, vulgar, whoſe <hi>Envy</hi> hath made them look a ſquint upon the work of the Miniſter, and whoſe buſy Idleneſſe finde fault which his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, conceaving the Curſe, <hi>in ſudore vnlous &amp;c.</hi> in the ſweat of thy browes ſhalt thou eate bread, not to reach his head; or that like an uſurer he lyes ſleeping in ſecurity, and therefore, that his maintenance takes him napping, here ſuch may receave an infallible Conviction.</p>
            <p>Pierius Hieroglyphically deſignes and ſindes out a true Scholler by the Hare, which ſleeps waking, with her eyes open, and wakes ſleeping with her oyes ſhutt, that is one, who ſeemes to contemplate Acting, and to Act in contemplation; Pitty it were to ſtart this Hare, from the forme; But alas, how ſubject howerly is this poore Hare to a ſuddaine ſurprize, yea without faire law ſhott at, and with ſuch Greedines as ſcarce miſt an Hare, In what danger ſits this Hare to be torne in Peeces, fleſh yea Skinne and all, nor will this alwayes ſuffice ſeldom ſuffocate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Praeda Canum lepus eſt vaſto, non implet Hiatus,</hi> the hare is a diſh for hounds, but groſſer Paunches ſhe cannot ſatisfy.</p>
            <p>Neither, have other Emblemiſts dealt penuriouſly, in their Annotations upon the ſerious Student, which diſcern him, by one eye ſhutt, and another open, <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> in his right hand, and the word of obſervation, <hi>vigilo,</hi> I watch; <hi>Heſperus,</hi> in his left hand, and the word, <hi>Dormio,</hi> I ſleepe; hence I collect they Argue, his juſt diviſion of the day and night, for theoricks and practicks, for Meditation, and Application.</p>
            <p>See, how he walks <hi>obstipo Capite,</hi> with his head awrie, his eyes perceing the earth; Heare but his ſilent murmuring, how his Spirits are gnawn aſunder and divided into peeces, by the worm of revolving invention.</p>
            <p>Perceive the worke of his Judgment, by his two lipps out ſtretcht, which are as <hi>Balances,</hi> to weigh his ſententious and ponderous expreſſions; yea think, how neere he conſumes himſelf, when ſpider like, he is ever weaving cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98863:9"/> webbs, for your ſoft and durable wearing, out of his own Bowells. Conſider that the firmament, the world and all creatures in heaven and earth are arguments propoſed for his underſtanding and diſputation, together with that <hi>principium primum, cauſa prima, ens entium,</hi> that <hi>eſſentiâ,</hi> and <hi>trinus perſonis,</hi> God, that one eternall Eſſence of three perſons, the Father, the Sonne, the holy Ghoſt, and his will to be revealed unto Chriſtians; for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing and effecting whereof, as there is little need of mundane Impediment, or the peoples diſcouragement, ſo great cauſe for the exerciſe of his prudence, which opportunely (I truſt) with your patience I may conſider, and that, very briefly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cicero,</hi> ſaith, it is <hi>ſcientia &amp; cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctio rerum, quas cupimus auf fugimus,</hi> the Apprehenſion and Election of thoſe things, which we are bound to ſeek or avoid; or it is <hi>Approbatio cauſarum, &amp; effectuum experientia,</hi> the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and accompt of cauſes with their Effects, doubtleſſe, it is the hand that layes out for all, the foot that walkes for all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the eare that heares for all and the very eye that conſtitutes all: It is (<hi>Ars vitae,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tully</hi>) as Phyſick is the Methodicall preſervative of our health, it is the Alarm of the Army, the Monitour of the School The watch in the Pockett, it is the predominant morall in mans Affections &amp; Actions, that whereas other vertues do, <hi>Inclinare,</hi> move men to Civility, and their paſſions to Regularity, this doth <hi>Imponere,</hi> im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe a neceſſity of wiſe Government in the ſoule: for no prudent man, as good no man.</p>
            <p>Nor is the vertue to be nicely diſliked becauſe Cardinall, or Confind to one office and Action of the Ambaſſadour, but generally to all.</p>
            <p>To his firſt Admiſſion into this holy Dignity, to his ſetting forth; yea it is his Companion in his journey betwixt earth and heaven, it comes along with him to the people, to whom he is ſent, and to ſumme up all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is his eye, his Eare, his mouth, his bracelett, It is every where, not circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, but as infinite, as the individualls, For ſince morall vertue, is an habit created in mans will by the holy Ghoſt, moving him to honeſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions agreeable to the line of Gods Law, and that prudence is one cheif, Pillar of mans reaſonable underſtanding, this Prudence wanting, or not practiſed, it muſt follow,</p>
            <p>A mans paſſions do ſubvert his reaſon, wiſdome is infatuated, His Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions contemning a judicious Government, and prudent moderation, expoſe him violently to unbridled courſes, irregular, exorbitant, and diſſolute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanours, or as the Schooles have it, <hi>per actus remiſſos habitus virtutis cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumpitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98863:10"/>
            <p>I cannot ſtand upon the varions diſtinctions of this prudence, as that perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, oeconomicall politicall, nor that of <hi>Cicero's pura &amp; impura, propria &amp; impropria,</hi> The firſt ſhewing a reſpective wiſdome, when a man feeles his own pulſe, and conſults himſelfe; The ſecond, more common, when hee ſends to the Phyſition, and is adviſed by another, that, which this hand leades mee to, at this time, is to thoſe effects, ſingular, and obſervable, in a <hi>religious prudence,</hi> and are as attendants upon this AMBASSADOVR, and they are theſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, <hi>Perfectè conſiderare,</hi> To conſider throughly, <hi>God, themſelves,</hi> their <hi>Ambaſſage,</hi> and the <hi>world;</hi> For, as he well replied, to an ignorant admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, of the ill ſucceſſe of thoſe things which with ſuch deliberations were at, tempted and acted, ſo, here it may make our anſwers, <hi>Conſultationum Domini Erant,</hi> they were Maſters of their deliberating conſultations, but not of the comming ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, is <hi>perfecte determinare,</hi> to determine throughly, <hi>Deo fidelitate ſeipſo, ſinceritate, populo, ſobrietate,</hi> with GOD by his fidel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, with himſelfe by his ſincerity, with the world by diſcretion and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That God bee not diſhonoured, for his want of judgment, nor him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe neglected, for want of due examination, nor the world abuſed and blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, in a matter of ſuch importance, as the Ambaſſage of there owne ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The third is <hi>perfecte applicare,</hi> throughly to apply himſelfe to God, and His Word, his <hi>Doctrine</hi> to Gods people, his life for their example, and his patience for their patterne, ſo that the people may joyfully receave the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, and hearken his Ambaſſage; That they may <hi>prudently</hi> embrace it, in its purity, obey it, as there line of godly life, in its ſanctity: And, that they may bee wrought, to an invincible courage, againſt all falſe Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, and Ambaſſages; And all gaine-ſayers of this Goſpell of <hi>Jeſus CHRIST,</hi> under what <hi>ſpecies</hi> of fained holineſſe, and ſeeming re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation whatſoever, yea <hi>Contra Angelum deſcendentem,</hi> againſt an Angell comming downe to ſuch a purpoſe; and ſo much for the firſt vertue, his pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>He that is juſtly <hi>prudent,</hi> is <hi>prudently juſt,</hi> for that is, not diſtinctions a badge by which, the true Ambaſſador is knowne.</p>
            <p>But upon, that <hi>Iuſtice, Quae ſibi, &amp; unicuique ſuum tribuit,</hi> morally I inſiſt not, nor upon that <hi>Originall Iuſtice,</hi> reaſon over ſenſuality; which <hi>Socrates</hi> pretily taught going thirſty to the wel, there drawing, the firſt bucket to power downe, and the next to drinke of, by which he ſhewed, the appetites ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98863:10"/> to reaſon, neither upon that naturall, univerſall, and Phyloſophicall Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, which being inſenſible, and imaginary. We contemplate by inward, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as the <hi>Ideas</hi> of <hi>Plato,</hi> nor that other artificiall, particular, and polliticall Iuſtice, which as the leaden Lesbian Rule, is made flexible, to times, perſons, and accidents, vet this way, were I to walk upon any diſtinction of Iuſtice in an Embaſſador, I ſhould render the deviſion in <hi>Iuſtitiam c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mutativam, et diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butivam;</hi> The firſt, practiſed betwixt themſelves and others privately, and by proportion <hi>Arithmeticall</hi> the ſecond meaſured, and done publikely, by <hi>Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricall proportion,</hi> whoſe direct ayme is <hi>praemium et ſupplicium,</hi> reward and puniſhment.</p>
            <p>But not to prejudice my text, You, nor my ſelfe, by injuſtice in digreſſion, I ſhall obſerve for my purpoſe, three ſpeciall notes, which as debts doe ingage the Embaſſador to a <hi>Religious juſtice. Deo, ſibi, ſuis.</hi> To God to himſelfe, to the world; Our bleſſed Saviour, Bipartires them, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord with all thy heart, thy God, and with all thy ſoule, and with all thy ſtrength, and thy neighbour as thy ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ambaſſage in my Text, comes not ſhort of the Angells doxology, and tydings to the Shepheards, Saint <hi>Luke</hi> 2. Here is <hi>glory to God, peace on earth, good will towards men;</hi> And the Iuſtice of this Ambaſſador, muſt bee Evangelically, Angelically, as was that Angelically, Evangelicall; Hee muſt know God, His maker, that ſent him; his Lord that intruſted him, and his Law-giver, that inveſted him, that as in other matters, from their knowledge iſſueth their honour done unto him; ſo in this, in them, who are ſent, and them to whom they are ſent, by ſuch knowledge in the one, and revelation to the other, there muſt be mutuall honour juſtly given unto God, and inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of piety, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y one to another.</p>
            <p>But this Iuſtice in the Ambaſſadour, muſt reach higher, by raiſing his devouteſt thoughts, to the contemplation of Gods Divinity, then which higher he cannot goe, for God, is <hi>terminus ad quem,</hi> the moſt exact indeavour of our conceits, infinitely tranſcending, all our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt and wiſeſt aymes, of mortall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, every Embaſſadour apart, may augment the <hi>Jdea,</hi> or notion of his Glory, according to the predicament of his own abillity; But God is above all, in Heaven and Earth, and the perfect knowledge of him, is <hi>Eſſential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Himſelfe,</hi> who being <hi>Actu infinitus, nonreperitur in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llo praedicamento,</hi> as <hi>Ariſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, this Embaſſador muſt know God, ſo far as to do him juſtice by true and ſeaſonable ſervice, anſwerable to his nature, which is <hi>ſpiritu et veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate:</hi> in ſpirit and truth; And the people, to whom this Embaſſadour comes, muſt deale juſtly with God, likewiſe, by receaving his Embaſſage, in purity of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98863:11"/> heart and ſpirit, <hi>Deus eſt ſpiritus,</hi> God is a ſpirit, <hi>&amp; ſi Deus eſt animus, ſit tibi purâmente Colendus,</hi> if God be a ſpirit, ye muſt worſhip him in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, yea the Father ſeeks for ſuch worſhippers, theſe are only right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, a pure ſpirit is a ſacrifice to God, an harmeleſle life, a ſpotleſſe ſoule: <hi>optimus animus pulcherrimus Dei cultus,</hi> a pure mind, is the beſt ſervice to God, the moſt religious worſhipping of God is to follow him, <hi>Amore, more, ore, re,</hi> and the only true ſerving and honoring of God in Prieſt, and people, is not evill, in ſumme, let this Embaſſadours Juſtice, and the peoples practiſe towards God, meet both in this, that it be, <hi>perfecta, pura, &amp; perpetua,</hi> perfect, that both only love him, pure, that both wiſely feare him, perpetuall, that both only and firmely beleive in him, and reſt in him.</p>
            <p>And let the Ambaſſadour, herein be juſt, to himſelf; that he pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually underſtand, the will of his King, and the weale of his people.</p>
            <p>In the firſt, wiſely and orderly to informe himſelf:</p>
            <p>In the ſecond, ſoberly and fully, to inſtruct the people, his honeſty muſt play the skillfull Organiſt, to touch well and truely according to Art, nor may he, at all times interweave a diſcourſe of Juſtice Pharaſaicall and legall, to the people to whom he comes, the Chriſtian only muſt be his rule; and then he is an Embaſſadour for Chriſt; when he is thus honeſtly juſt to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; I ſay honeſtly, for herein, what health is in the body, the ſame is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly in the ſoule, <hi>Salus animae is honeſtas corporis;</hi> And to ſumme up all, the Prophets <hi>Baſar</hi> and the Angells <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Good and new, joyfull and ſeaſonable, Tidings, of Chriſt promiſed, of Chriſt exhibited, muſt from his mouth dropp like Soveraign oyle of Gladnes to annoint the ſwelling heart of the miſerable wounded man, whom the Prieſt and Levite, the Law could not ſtand to pity, or look upon to remedy; this oyle, thus dropping, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſoule of a Sinner, melted and diſſolved, (by ſence and ſorrowes for ſinne) to bitter teares, will in theſe liquids, appeare uppermoſt; and as the oint ment upon <hi>Aarons</hi> head, will not only ſupple himſelf, but runne down upon the skirts of his Clothing, the meaneſt of his Auditours.</p>
            <p>Oh, the Excellency, of ſuch an Ambaſſadour, the meaſure, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion and Comlineſſe of his body, is wiſdome, and ſpirituall beauty, the riches of his ſpirit, are the Gifts of the ſpirit, and his ſciences, and his Juſtice to God and man, is as that noble <hi>Aptnes,</hi> which diſpoſeth him to all vertues, and holines, and ſo much for this Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98863:11"/> from that I have ſpoken by neceſſary conſequence you may deduce the prime ſtrength of an Ambaſſadour to depend upon well grounded intelligence and practicall wiſedome, which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuch a man of God intimates by his Urim and Thummim, ſo much diſcipline an ordinary eare might take in, from that golden Bell and Pomegranate which ſurrounded the hem of the Prieſts robe; this is that onely delightfull ſound and pleaſant taſt, which through the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the holy Ghoſt, the voice of the Father &amp; the Son, is effectuall to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſin-ſpotted ſoul &amp; dumb ſinner unto purity, &amp; Hallelujahs everlaſting.</p>
            <p>I omit the ſignificant illuſtrations unto this duty, which the inſeparable and particular ornaments of the Tabernacle might lead me, and content my ſelfe with thoſe rules which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> applied to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> Hold faſt a forme of ſound words, giving attendance to reading and doctrine, exhort and convince, be apt and able to teach, which doctrine clearly oppoſeth, all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit quarrelling with words, frothy, and ſcummy-jangling language, and all peeviſh, theeviſh, treacherous and traiterous documents.</p>
            <p>Thus like the noted Muſician, I have ſate ſo long upon this Text, that I feare I have not kept time. I confeſſe my ſelfe unprepared for farther proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of any part coincident to, and with this Text: I beſeech you, ſuffer my jejune and dry oratory to expreſſe an application of what hath beene hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto propounded, which through Gods aſſiſtance, and your patience, I ſhall thus epitomize.</p>
            <p>1. It inſtructs the Ambaſſadour with all meet preparation conſiderately to undertake his Embaſſage, for they are the ſavour of life, to life, or death, to death, to the people to whom they come; and to that office muſt bee required more then ordinary circumſpection, the iſſues whereof are of ſuch extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary concernment. Hence <hi>Moſes</hi> complaines of his want of utterance, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence; and S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Who is ſufficient for theſe things? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 16. The trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures compriſed in the rich Casket of ſacred Scripture, with which they are by God intruſted to communicate unto the people, are for profundity ſo great, and for extent ſo large, that I may reſume that of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Who is ſufficient, &amp;c. it juſtly purſues the runners of theſe times, which without miſſion or commiſſion lay hands on conſecrated things, whom I lovingly adviſe to ſtay at Iericho till their beards be growne; for if Deacons muſt firſt be tryed, and then Miniſter if they be found faithfull, much more ſhould workmen of more eminent faculty not aſſume unto themſelves a calling, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſome <hi>Timothy</hi> or <hi>Titus</hi> duly authoriſed by a ſacred ſymboll of manuall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, give them externall appointment to that function: Gods holy Spirit muſt give them primary and private motion, their owne conſciences evident and certaine juſtification, the Church legall ordination; and though at this time there is great queſtion about the forme of ordination, yet in all ages, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98863:12"/> in all well ordered places, there have beene certaine conſtitutions, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons for admitting of men upon triall into ſacred orders; and I finde not that ever the ſetled order of any Church for ſuch purpoſes, hath beene ſo calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niated and branded as at this time this of ours. Hence I ſhall not feare to conclude, that who ever ſhall propheſie or preach in this Church without examination, approbation and faculty, by preſent authority, commeth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and as a falſe Prophet, I take it our duty to beware of him.</p>
            <p>2. The name of an Ambaſſadour implies faithfulneſſe in the declaration of his Embaſſage, he comes not forth without inſtructions what he ſhall ſay and doe, nor may he adde or diminiſh from Gods word, he muſt not create unto himſelfe a fools paradiſe, and walke up and downe there, ſet up a throne and judge there, he muſt fiſh in Gods Sea and World, not lanch into another of his owne making, nor ſaile with pleaſure in old wives fables, or iſſues of his owne braines; if he have an itch within him to long for that which neither the place nor ſeaſon affords, ſome unheard of unparalleld perfection in Uto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia; it muſt be carefully adverted unto, and cured before it ſpread, or the people ſmell it: Gods true Ambaſſadour muſt content himſelfe with the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of God diſcovered in the depth of his word, and the height of his works: for the bleſſed Spirit reveales nothing but that which is the will of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Sonne, <hi>John</hi> 16. 14. and Gods Angells we may imagine in old time ſpake neither more nor leſſe, then what they had declared unto them in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and an Ambaſſadour on earth muſt not dare to tranſgreſſe that celeſtiall proportion.</p>
            <p>3. The fanaticall Zelots of our times judge all learning, but Scripture, the language of the Beaſt, and that there is no uſe of Latin, except ordinary, or as much as will keepe the necke from an halter; and there can bee no pure preaching of the word with them, except Univerſities downe, and they come up, not directed by the letter, but Spirit; they object the Apoſtles were illiterate men, and yet by the Spirit they underſtood all myſteries and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and I would have them without education to their tongues, in Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall manner ſpeake to the Jewes, and Indians, and other like with us, and it ſhould be to me a probable inducement ſooner to confide in their abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to direct us in that truth in our owne tongue, which they fondly pretend Academicks miſſe of, and I dare ſafely queſtion, whether ſuch by their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſpirit can effect more without artificiall inſtructions, then ſuch as with the knowledge of Arts have the aſſiſtance of the true Spirit of God. Thence I conclude, though Gods ſacred Word ſhould eſpecially have prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency in all learning, and all Gods Ambaſſadours, yet how ſhall this word be ſafely interpreted, &amp; the ſenſe truly rendred without knowledge in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginalls, Tranſlations, &amp; ancient Commentaries, therefore to uſe humane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98863:12"/> as <hi>Hagar</hi> to attend <hi>Sarah,</hi> and Arts and expoſitors aſſiſtance, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of learned men, as <hi>Joſhua</hi> the Gibeonites, (who upon the grounds and landmarkes of antiquity, old bootes old ſhooes, moulded bread, were admitted to carry water for the Iſrael of God) is lawfull, and for ought I read not in any age before gainſayed in ſuch vulgar impudencies, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent inſolencies as in this.</p>
            <p>4. But how aſhamed is a learned and wiſe King of a fooliſh and ignorant Ambaſſadour, and how God ſuffers in his glory when Miniſters want know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to inſtruct the people? Becauſe thou haſt rejected knowledge, I will alſo reject thee, thou ſhalt bee no Prieſt to mee, ſaith the Lord by the Prophet <hi>Hoſea:</hi> theſe are the dumbe Dogs ſpoken of by another of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, unto whom if the booke be tendred, may be anſwered, <hi>non legit ut cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus,</hi> he dreams and ſees viſions, bookes ſealed, and his profitableſt docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is the peoples nocument, his beſt doctrine is the peoples ſcandall, wherein he muſt acknowledge that he is no Prophet, nor Prophets ſonne, he never ſaw the Schooles of the Prophets, he is ſome husbandman, herdman, or at beſt, a cobler, hatter, horſerubber, leatherſeller, or tailor, and ſo skipping up to reforme the magnificat in the City or Country, before he had his <hi>nunc dimittis</hi> in the Univerſity, his doctrine is ignorance, his uſe error, the Pulpit (the true ſeat of ſpirituall judgement, and divine oratory,) is ſtuffed with old ſaddles, empty pictures, brainſicke and railing ſuperfluities: and hence it is that the hearers Camelion like, live upon aire and winde.</p>
            <p>But conſidering the weight of this ſpirituall Ambaſſage in all actions and circumſtances thereto pertinent. The Tables of the Law, in the diſcuſſing whereof large Volumes will not containe the Caſes of Conſcience thence ſtill emergent, conſidering the Ambaſſadours skill required in Ethickes, Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomiques, Politiques, Hiſtories, Chronology, Geography, Philoſophy, Tongues, Rhetorique, Logique, holy Scripture, myſteries of Propheſie, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Schoolemen, Polemicall Divinity, and Controverſie.</p>
            <p>The Arguments of Papiſts, Atheiſts, Turkes, and Sectaries, to bee reſolv'd and refell'd.</p>
            <p>Miſpriſions in Hiſtory, Propheſie, Tongues, Caſes of Conſcience, which ariſe (to the great diſturbance and unhinging of Chriſtian truth) to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed.</p>
            <p>Many divine ſentences and other paſſages without conference inexpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable.</p>
            <p>Conſidering theſe (and infinite more of this nature) individuals to his fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, what uſe ſhould the true Church make of arrogant ideots, and perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptory illiterates? whoſe zeale without knowledge, like mettle in blinde horſes, deſtroy the riders, ſtumbling upon they care not, know not whom?
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98863:13"/> Why doe we put children to remove great timber? blinde men to conduct us in unknowne paths? Doth a mans curioſity reſtraine his <hi>wearing</hi> Apparrell from a Botcher, and his diſtruſt preſerve his dying body from a Mountebank, and ſhall not true zeale to his ſoules <hi>eternall</hi> life, warrant his ſpeciall care; to what doctrine, and whoſe ſpirituall overſight he ſubmits himſelfe? If wee make no conſcience of this, we make conſcience of nothing, and conſcience nothing.</p>
            <p>And by this meanes the Ambaſſadours ignorance, and the peoples pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe, ſedition and hereſie takes place of religion and piety, and as well ſound doctrine, as ancient diſcipline, is transformed into a fable, and ſcoffe, and the people having caſt off all true obedience to Gods law, benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med conſcience, and rejected right judgement and true holineſſe, make no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing true doctrine but what pleaſeth them.</p>
            <p>But if antiquity for doctrine and diſcipline ſhall beare no authority with them, if they will not follow <hi>Moſes</hi> advice, inquire of the dayes before them, even from one end of heaven to the other, if they account not the Doctors and Hiſtories of the Church unpartiall which lived before, ſuch ignorance in the one, and licentiouſneſſe in the other, were ſo open and impudent, ſuch blaſphemies &amp; queſtions were moved, as are now too frequent to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, Jeſus Chriſt, and his Word, and the offence of good men: and if they will circumciſe the Church to themſelves onely, and not to the rules of the ancient Scriptures, Apoſtles, and Teachers, damning all but themſelves, I hope you cannot be offended if I deliberate whether I would be of ſuch a Church, whereof for ought I know never any were before themſelves: wee may gird on our ſwords of knowledge to help us in theſe perillous journies, but the beſt acceſſory for protection and direction is Gods providence and wiſdome to his ſervants, which is timely and needful.</p>
            <p>Having in the laſt uſe, left lawleſſe Ignorance in the Pulpit of godly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, what ungodly and improbable deductions wil thence be compelled, is eaſie, though diſmall io conceive. For doth not the Papiſt preach hence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility, and with <hi>Campian</hi> cry, <hi>Templum, Templum,</hi> the Church, the Church? and the Schiſmaticks in their invective Pamphlets uſe the words of <hi>Iſa. 62. 1. For Sions ſake I will not hold my tongue, and for Jeruſalems ſake I will not reſt,</hi> and are not both our enemies, the Papiſts for tyranny, and the other labouring for Anarchy?</p>
            <p>Are not mercenary Levites abounding with us, the Devils dawbers, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <hi>placentia,</hi> and ſowing pillowes under mens elbowes, ſpeaking good of evill, and evill of good, men-pleaſures, blinding Iſraels ſinne, and taking a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for iniquity? Doe not Prophets propheſie falſly, and men love to have it ſo? and are not the times ſuch, I feare not to ſpeake, giving God the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98863:13"/> that he that departs from ſuch iniquity, maketh himſelfe a prey? Do not prophaneneſſe, hardheartedneſſe, murmuring, contumelies, revilings, envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, luke warmeneſſe, dwell amongſt us? Are not theſe diſeaſes catching, Epidemicall? Is it not to be feared they poſſeſſe the whole body of the land? Are not fiſhers of men, turn'd fiſhers of money, fiſhers of women? Did not the Devill tempt <hi>Eve</hi> firſt, and then overcome <hi>Adam?</hi> Is it not hence that ſilly women are led captive, laden with ſinfull luſts? are not they firſt wrought upon by ſtrange doctrines as meanes to trap their husbands? what reaſon can you give for this, ſave that their weakneſſe makes way to receive falſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, and gives them more confident to broach them; or becauſe they ſeeke not God in the truth, or becauſe their wits are ſhort, and their tongues long.</p>
            <p>Are there not a generation of men riſen up, which our Proteſtant forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers never knew, whoſe hearts as if they were hewne out of hard rocks, or as if they had ſuckt the milke of Wolves, (as it is reported the firſt founder of Rome did) relent not to ſee their native Country made nothing elſe but a ſhambles of butchers and blood? <hi>Alexander</hi> when he ſaw the dead corps of <hi>Darius,</hi> and <hi>Marcus Marcellus, Syracuſa</hi> burne, and <hi>Titus</hi> Jeruſalem laid even with the ground, (though enemies) could not abſtaine from teares: theſe quite contrary mourne not with Jeruſalem, nor helpe it with prayers in this ſad time of unnaturall calamity.</p>
            <p>Are there not men pretending right to the Ambaſſadours calling, who have none in juſtice to it, men Canon mouth'd, and yet living by no Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall rule, no Logicians, yet full of fallacies, right Carters upon <hi>Seton,</hi> whip and goe, bellowing like Buls of Baſan, balls of wild fire, downe with her, downe with her to the ground; Gunpowder arguments againſt Church and State, who in their owne ſenſe, notwithſtanding will be martyrs, Saints, Cathariſts: but if thoſe be martyrs who are murtherers? if theſe be Saints who are Scythians? and if theſe be Cathariſts who are Canibals?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, this doctrine reflects upon the people, and teaches them ſpirituall obedience, Obey them that have rule over you: and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians, <hi>I beſeech you know them that labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and have them in eſtimation for their workes ſake.</hi> To this purpoſe is it that God ſo dearly accompts them in Scripture, that the King is directed to aske counſell of God at the mouth of the Prieſt: and King <hi>Salomon</hi> termes them the maſters of Aſſemblies, to this purpoſe, there preaching is termed propheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the hearers are ſaid to ſit at their feet, and not upon their skirts; to teach them leſſons of love, and religious reverence.</p>
            <p>But alas, this kingdome cannot ſmother it, <hi>The fathers have eaten ſowre grapes, and the childrens teeth are ſet on edge.</hi> In old time it was Ghoſtly Father,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98863:14"/> but now <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſt, Jeſuits, Canterbury whelps, none of Gods Prieſts, mans Prieſts, not inſpired, nor called, nor led by the Spirit: nay the moſt Chriſtian and judiciouſly godly Ambaſſadours in this City have in their charges, and in their occaſionall grave walkings beene derided and exploded. But if natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lawes, and hiſtoricall teſtimonies produce ſuch examples of cruelties and wrongs, for the abuſe &amp; blood of Ambaſſadours, then I ſay the Lord cometh even within a little while, behold the God of Angels and men cometh with thouſands and ten thouſands, to take vengeance upon the men of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for their barbarous entertainment of many of his Ambaſſadours, coming meekly unto them with Chriſtmas in their mouthes, <hi>Evangelium gaudii,</hi> a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell of joy, Chriſt Jeſus an eternall Saviour, borne in the time of peace, and for their redemption.</p>
            <p>I will end my Sermon with the prayer of our forefathers, in a part of the firſt Engliſh Lytany, ſet out in the dayes of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, From all ſedition and privy conſpiracy, from the tyranny of the Biſhop of Rome, and all his deteſtable enormities, from all falſe doctrine and hereſie, from hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, from contempt of thy word and Commandements.</p>
            <p>Unto which by the aſſiſtance of Gods Spirit I will adde:</p>
            <p>From all Jeſuits, Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, Socinians, Arminians, rebels, traitors, ſectaries, and turbulent ſpirits, good Lord deliver us.</p>
            <p>And that Gods glory may for ever ſhine upon us, we pray,</p>
            <p>That it may pleaſe him to be ſtill with this Church and Nation, that hee would ſay to the deſtroying Angell, it is enough here, and elſe where.</p>
            <p>That the Goſpell of his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt, the moſt holy and juſt Lord, be ſoundly preached, and obediently and purely practiſed.</p>
            <p>That the true Proteſtant Religion, I meane the whole body of Doctrine revealed in Gods written word, abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation, eſtabliſhed in Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> his dayes, may yet and ever continue amongſt us.</p>
            <p>That ſuch diſcipline may be uſed, as Gods Saints may ſerve him in his places of worſhip in all comelineſſe and decency.</p>
            <p>That God would ſtill continue the Kings heart in ſincerity, to his glory, and the true Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>That God would cover his head in the day of battell, and protect him from all his enemies, and knit faſt in one truth and peace, him and his people.</p>
            <p>That we may all keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.</p>
            <p>That we may enjoy peace ſupernall with God, internall of conſcience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and fraternall one with another.</p>
            <p>We beſeech thee to heare us good Lord.</p>
            <p>Thus living Angellically in peace on earth, we ſhall by Jeſus Chriſt the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98863:14"/> Prince of peace, pertake of peace with Angels in heaven, here by participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there by conſummation; where is no place for ſedition, for their bleſſe is orderly, and their happineſſe everlaſting, where we ſhall ſing this unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous triſagion, holy, holy, holy, Lord God of Sabbath, heaven and earth are full of the Majeſty of thy glory: Glory be to thee, O Lord, moſt high God the Father, and to Jeſus Chriſt the everlaſting ſoule-ſaving Sonne, and the truly God, and bleſſed and holy Spirit, eternally proceeding from both.</p>
            <p>To whom, trinity in unity, and unity in trinity, be aſcribed, as is moſt due, from the bottome of our hearts, all honour, glory, power, praiſe, wiſdome, righteouſneſſe, mercy and judgement, the reſt of this Lords day, hencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and for ever; and let all that heare me this day, ſay, Amen, Amen, Amen, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
